A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, M-R FA393
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, M-R
1911-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA393
60 Cubic Feet Boxes 273-422,
Actual extent is unknown.
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation diaries:
Officers of the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and its staff members in the field often visited educational, scientific and research institutions and laboratories in many parts of the world to maintain contacts and assess work being done. Officers and field staff frequently conferred with government officials regarding the operation of the RF's programs. In order to preserve accurate records for the guidance of other RF officers, those who carried on these activities kept diaries of their day-to-day contacts and impressions. These diaries were sent to the RF office, where they circulated among officers and staff to the extent deemed advisable.
Rockefeller Foundation:
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
File Plan note
RG 12
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office
Scope and Contents note
Rockefeller Foundation officers' diaries:
Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
Diaries frequently contain information given in confidence, and were thus treated as confidential., The period covered is approximately 1911-1992.
Conditions Governing Access note
Officers' diaries are open for scholarly research provided that (1) the diarist is deceased and (2) the volume to be examined is at least twenty years old. All reasonable efforts will be made to determine the fate of the diarist(s), but if such efforts are fruitless then the material will remain closed to scholarly research until 100 years after the officer's year of birth.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries include:
FA391 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries A-E.
FA392 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries F-L.
FA394 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries S-Z.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by surname.
Arts; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; African Americans; Medical sciences; Philanthropy -- United States; Life sciences; Humanities; Epidemics; Diseases; Charities; Philanthropy; Race and society; Public health
- Magoon, Estus H.
  Central America; Greece
  - 1938 November- 1939 August (Box 273)
  - 1937, 1939 (Box 273)
  - 1946-1948 (Box 273)
  - 1950, 1953-1955 (Box 274)
- Mahaffy, Alexander F.
  - 1935-1937 (Box 274)
  - 1938-1940 (Box 274)
  - 1941-1946 (Box 275)
- Maier, John
  - 1946-1953 (Box 276)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 276)
  - 1953 (Box 276)
  - 1954 (Box 277)
  - 1955 (Box 277)
  - 1954-1956 (Box 277)
  - 1956 (Box 278)
  - 1957 (Box 278)
  - 1957 (Box 278)
  - 1958 (Box 279)
  - Index, Diary, 1959 January-May (Box 279)
  - 1959 June-December (Box 279)
  - 1960 (Box 279)
  - 1961 (Box 280)
  - 1962 (Box 280)
  - 1963 (Box 280)
  - 1964 (Box 281)
  - 1965 (Box 281)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 281)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 282)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 282)
  - 1972-1977 (Box 282)
  - Index, 1951-1970 (Box 283)
- Makinsky, Alexander
  - 1940 (Box 283)
  - 1941 (Box 283)
  - 1942 (Box 283)
- Mann, Albert R.
  Biographical/Historical note
  Albert R. Mann (1880-1947) studied agriculture at Cornell University, and was graduated in 1904. Mann was appointed Assistant Professor in 1908 at Cornell, Secretary-Editor-Registrar in 1908, Professor of Rural Social Organization in 1915, Acting Dean in 1916, Dean in 1917, and finally Provost in 1931. From 1924-1926 Mann directed the International Education Board's (IEB) program of agricultural education and rehabilitation in Europe. Mann returned to Cornell in 1926, but the IEB program continued by his associate, C. B. Hutchison until conclusion in 1928. In 1936 the General Education Board (GEB) engaged Mann to survey the problems of agricultural colleges in the southern United States, and produced the report "Rural Economic and Social Studies in Southern Institutions". Mann was then appointed Vice President and Director of the GEB in 1937. After retiring from the GEB in 1946, Mann then joined the Natural Sciences Division of the Rockefeller Foundation on a part-time basis, to lead the agricultural program. In the winter of 1946-1947, Mann travelled to Germany to visit universities and research institutions interview former fellows and professors the Foundation had contacts with before World War II, and appraise the educational needs of those centers. Mann died on February 21, 1947 in New York, while returning from Germany. For more information on Mann's career, see the Rockefeller Foundation Trustees Bulletin, March 1947, pages 1-8.
  Scope and Contents
  Albert R. Mann's logs (diaries) for 1924-1927 are variously titled "Log, Summary of Interviews Inspections, and Other Activities, A.R. Mann, Director of Agricultural Education for Europe, International Education Board, and C.B. Hutchison (his Associate)". Each log focuses on a specific country or region. Logs dating from 1926-1927 are primarily authored by C.B. Hutchison.
  Related Materials
  Albert R. Mann's diaries from 1937-1939 and 1943-1946 are found in the General Education Board records (FA058), Series 12: Diaries, box 18-20.
  Indexing to Albert R. Mann's logs is provided by the International Education Board records, Albert R. Mann and Harry Luman Russell logs index (FA769).
  Agriculture
  - Log 1: Great Britain and Ireland (First Report), 1924 August 1-September 30 (Box 284)
  - Log 2: Italy (First Report), 1924 October 1-November 15 (Box 284)
  - Log 3: Austria (First Report), 1924 November 19-December 1 (Box 284)
  - Log 4: Czechoslovakia and Russia (First Report), 1924 December 2-17 (Box 284)
  - Log 5: Greece (First Report), 1924 November 16-25 (Box 284)
  - Log 6: Bulgaria (First Report), 1924 November 27-December 12 (Box 284)
  - Log 7: Romania (First Report), 1924 December 13-29 (Box 284)
  - Log 8: Hungary (First Report), 1924 December 30-1925 January 24 (Box 284)
  - Log 9: Yugoslavia (First Report), 1925 January 26-February 4 (Box 285)
  - Log 10: Germany (First Report), 1924 December 18-1925 January 7 (Box 285)
  - Log 11: Poland (First Report), 1925 January 8-17 (Box 285)
  - Log 12-13: Latvia and Estonia (First Report), 1925 January 18-29 (Box 285)
  - Log 14: Finland (First Report), 1925 January 30-February 7 (Box 285)
  - Log 15: Sweden (First Report), 1925 February 9-18 and March 1-2 (Box 285)
  - Log 16: Norway (First Report), 1925 February 19-27 (Box 285)
  - Log 17.1: Germany (Second Report), Part 1: Summary, 1925 March 22-30 (Box 285)
    Includes photographs.
  - Log 17.2: Germany (Second Report), Part 2: Agricultural Institutions and Organizations, 1925 March 22-30 (Box 286)
  - Log 18: Lithuania (First Report), 1925 June 17-20 (Box 286)
  - Log 19: Belgium (First Report), 1925 September 25-October 3 (Box 286)
  - Log 20: Denmark (First Report), 1925 March 4, November 9-18 (Box 286)
  - Log 21: Holland (First Report), 1925 November 20-28 (Box 286)
  - Log 22: Spain (First Report), 1925 December 11-18 (Box 286)
  - Log 23: Great Britain and Ireland (Second Report), 1925-July 24-1926 March 18 (Box 287)
  - Log 24.1: Italy (Second Report), 1925 March 5-May 5 (Box 287)
  - Log 24.2: Misc notes in connection with travel to interview fellowship candidates in Denmark, Norway, Sweden, Finland, Estonia, Latvia, Poland, and Czechoslovakia, 1926 February 6-23 (Box 287)
  - Log 24.3: Misc notes in connection with travel to interview fellowship candidates in Italy, Greece, Bulgaria, Romania, Hungary and Yugoslavia, 1926 April 12-May 8 (Box 287)
  - Log 25: Sweden (Second Report), 1926 September 25-October 1; 1927 August 9; 1927 December 7-8 (Box 287)
  - Log 26: Norway (Second Report), 1926 October 3-4; 1927 December 5-6 (Box 287)
  - Log 27: Germany (Third Report), 1925 November 2 (Box 287)
  - Log 28: Hungary (Second Report), 1925 November 14-23; 1926 November 10-11 (Box 287)
  - Log 29: Austria (Second Report), 1925 November 7-13, December 13-15; 1926 November 7-9 (Box 287)
  - Log 30: Czechoslovakia (Second Report), 1925 November 3-6 (Box 287)
  - Log 31: Romania (Second Report), 1925 November 24-30 (Box 287)
  - Log 32: Poland (Second Report), 1926 October 25-November 6 (Box 288)
  - Log 33: Great Britain (Third Report), 1927 December 9-15 (Box 288)
  - Log 34: Finland (Second Report), 1927 December 9-12 (Box 288)
  - 1940 (Box 288)
  - 1941 (Box 288)
  - 1942 (Box 289)
- Mann, Charles K.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restricted - RF Officer Diaries.
  Restricted - Living RF Officer.
  - 1974-1976 (Box 289)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 289)
- Marmor, Michael
  - 1971-1973 (Box 290)
- Marshall, John
  John Marshall (1903-1980) was born in Portland, Maine, completed undergraduate (1925) and graduate (1928) studies, and taught in the English department (1927-1933) at Harvard University. In 1933 he joined the Rockefeller Foundation as Assistant (later Associate) Director of the newly formed Humanities program, and from 1933 to 1940 served as a Director of Education with the General Education Board.
  As an officer with the Rockefeller Foundation in a newly formed program, Mr. Marshall explored not only specific projects, but the concept of the humanities as a field. Mr. Marshall developed a concern in promoting world-wide culture, with a special interest in the Near East. The Rockefeller Foundation funding for the arts and humanities from 1933 to 1950 was approximately $4 million. Between 1951 and 1960, the support increased to $8.4 million, supporting projects in areas including language, radio, and motion pictures.
  Mr. Marshall remained an Associate Director for the Humanities program when appointed as the first director for the newly acquired Villa Serbelloni in Bellagio, Italy, in 1959. The Villa was (and continues to be) used as a retreat for scholars in a variety of disciplines who were were working on intensive projects and as a conference center for international meetings focused on significant issues or scientific developments. As director, Marshall worked to develop the direction for the Villa, while maintaining his connections with the European humanities community.
  John Marshall was married to Mary Gardner Marshall (1927-1960) and Charlotte Trowbridge Koechl Marshall (1961), and had two children from his first marriage, Mary Elizabeth Scott and Ann (Sister Mary John OSB). He was the author of "Classic Cooking" (1959).
  Mr. Marshall retired from the Foundation in 1970 and died in 1980.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. Digital files and user copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  Italy
  - Index, 1933 June 23-1934 June 15; Marshall, John; Rockefeller Foundation; 14 pages (Reel M Mar 1, Frame 1, Box 291)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Index to the diary June 1933 - June 1934. Organized alphabetically, including names and subjects.
    United States; Literature, Modern; Library science; Ireland; indexes (reference sources); Humanities; France; English literature; Bibliography; England; Belgium
  - 1933 June 23-1934 June 15, Rockefeller Foundation; Marshall, John; 181 pages (Box 291, Reel M Mar 1, Frame 15)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Marshall discusses the current state of higher education in the humanities at universities in the United States, Ireland, England, France, and Belgium. He speaks with professors and university librarians on the development of RF programs in classical & modern literature and the education of professional librarians in the United States during the fall of 1933 and early months of 1934. He notes the names of promising graduate students deserving fellowships, as recommended by interviewed faculty members. Marshall also gives a detailed account of a meeting of the American Library Association in Chicago (Oct. 20-22, 1933). Marshall then gives a detailed account his tour of Ireland, England, France, and Belgium during April - June 1934.
    Ireland; Literature, Modern; Humanities; Library science; France; English literature; United States; England; Diaries; Bibliography; Belgium
  - Index, 1934 July 11-December 31; Rockefeller Foundation; Marshall, John; 16 pages (Box 291, Reel M Mar 1, Frame 196)
    Index to the diary June - December 1934. Organized alphabetically, including names and subjects.
    United States; Literature, Modern; Academic achievement; Humanities; English literature; Library science; indexes (reference sources)
  - 1934 July 11-December 31, Rockefeller Foundation; Marshall, John; 160 pages (Box 291, Reel M Mar 1, Frame 212)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Marshall discusses possible projects expanding humanities programs and library collections at universities in the United States. He also gives short biographies of potential RF fellows in these fields. Marshall visits several private high schools in the New York City area, including Bronxville Senior High School (Sept. 20-21, 1934) and the Fieldston School (Oct. 9-10, 1934). He attends several seminars and conferences for professionals in the field of Education. Marshall also tours several colleges and high schools in Ohio and upstate New York (Oct. 22 - Nov. 1, 1934), writes extensively on the courses offered at Sarah Lawrence College (Nov. 13, 1934), and the courses offered at General College, University of Minnesota (Dec. 4-8, 1934), while making a tour of several schools in Minnesota, Iowa, and Missouri.
    Academic achievement; Humanities; English literature; Literature, Modern; Library science; United States; Diaries
  - 1935 January 2-September 20, Marshall, John; Rockefeller Foundation; 171 pages (Box 291, Reel M Mar 1, Frame 375)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Marshall discusses the current state of educational broadcasting via radio in the United States. He speaks with professionals in the education departments at NBC, CBS, and RCA, along with academics creating radio programs for these networks. Marshall also speaks with professionals in the field of classical music, and discusses the current state of musical education. Marshall visits several universities and radio broadcasting organizations in the Midwest (April 1935) and discusses the state of educational broadcasting via radio. He then attends a meeting of the Ohio Radio Education Association (May 6-8, 1935) and a meeting of the Federal Communications Commission (May 15-16, 1935). Marshall also visits the Brooklyn Museum (April 11, 1935) and discusses the public educational programs at the museum. During the summer of 1935 Marshall speaks with professionals and academics in the fields of music, theater, film, literature, and the visual arts, and discusses various projects relating to public education in these fields.
    Diaries; Educational broadcasting; Humanities; Music; Radio; Radio in education; United States
  - Index, 1935 September 11-December 31; Rockefeller Foundation; Marshall, John; 11 pages (Reel M Mar 1, Frame 546, Box 291)
    Index to the diary September - December 1935. Organized alphabetically, including names and subjects.
    indexes (reference sources)
  - 1935 September 11-December 31, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 144 pages (Reel M Mar 1, Frame 557, Box 291)
    Scope and Contents note
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an assistant director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program focuses on a greater means of cultural diffusion instead of research. In the United States grants were made to museums, drama, film and radio. This diary surveys humanities programs in the field of education in the western United States. The diary includes "Iowa State College Extension Service" budget statement.
    Drama; Language and languages; Museums; Oriental art; Pottery; United States; Theater; Diaries; Radio; Music
  - 1936 January 2-August 21, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 242 pages (Box 291, Reel M Mar 1, Frame 701)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an assistant director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program focuses on creating a greater means of cultural diffusion. In the United States grants were made to museums, drama, film and radio. This diary includes information on humanities in the field of education and discusses various educational broadcasting programs with universities, NBC, CBS and other organizations. Marshall travels to the Midwest to survey University of Minneapolis' Visual Education Department and various educational broadcasting university programs and local broadcasting organizations.
    Radio in education; Radio; Music; Libraries; Visual education; United States; Humanities; Educational broadcasting; Education; Diaries; Drama; CBS Broadcasting Inc; Carnegie Corporation of New York; National Broadcasting Company
  - Index, 1936 August 20-December 31; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 12 pages (Box 291, Reel M Mar 1, Frame 943)
    12 pages; arranged alphabetically.
  - 1936 August 20-December 31, Marshall, John; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 175 pages (Reel M Mar 1, Frame 955, Box 291)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an assistant director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program focuses on creating a greater means of cultural diffusion. Grants were primarily made to museums, drama, film and radio. In this diary Marshall travels to London to survey education in the arts, libraries, film and radio. He travels to France to report on current developments in radio broadcasting and attends the Intergovernmental Conference to Conclude a Convention on Broadcasting in the Interest of Peace at the League of Nations in Geneva. The Worldwide Broadcasting Foundation's experiment in developing radio program of cultural and education value with the W1XAL radio station is detailed as well.
    Broadcasting; Educational broadcasting; Education; Music; Libraries; Radio in education; Radio; France; Film; Language and languages; Humanities; United States; Diaries; Carnegie Corporation of New York; CBS Broadcasting Inc; British Broadcasting Corporation; League of Nations; National Broadcasting Company
  - 1937 January 7-July 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 214 pages (Reel M Mar 2, Frame 1, Box 292)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an assistant director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program focuses on creating a greater means of cultural diffusion. Grants were primarily made to museums, drama, film and radio. In this diary Marshall attends various conferences of the Federal Radio Education Committee, and the School and College Conference on English. The Worldwide Broadcasting Foundation's experiment in developing radio program of cultural and education value with the W1XAL radio station is detailed as well.
    Diaries; Educational broadcasting; Humanities; Broadcasting; Radio in education; Radio; United States. Federal Communications Commission; CBS Broadcasting Inc; British Broadcasting Corporation; National Broadcasting Company
  - 1937 September 2-December 31, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Marshall, John; 139 pages (Box 292, Reel M Mar 2, Frame 217)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. John Marshall is an assistant director of the Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities Division. The program focuses on creating a greater means of cultural diffusion. Grants were primarily made to museums, drama, film and radio. In this diary Marshall travels to University of Wisconsin and University of Minnesota. He attends the Conference on the Stratford Language Arts Study. The progress on various radio broadcasting projects as well as motion picture projects is documented.
    Radio in education; Radio; United States; Film; Motion pictures; Diaries; Humanities; Canada; Broadcasting; National Broadcasting Company; British Broadcasting Corporation
  - 1938 January 4-December 29, Marshall, John; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 251 pages (Reel M Mar 2, Frame 356, Box 292)